<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//SWEETOHM//DTD article 1.0//EN"
                         "../dtd/article.dtd">

<article author="Michel CASABIANCA"
         email="casa@sweetohm.net"
         date="2004-01-06"
         id="codeguide-tips"
         lang="en">

 <title>Extend CodeGuide features</title>

 <abstract>
  <p>This article presents CodeGuide extensions to launch JUnit tests,
   open a BeanShell console and Ant builds within this IDE.</p>
 </abstract>

 <text>

  <sect><title>The Code Guide IDE</title>

   <p>CodeGuide (which evaluation version can be downloaded on
    <link url="http://www.omnicore.com">Omnicore's web site</link>)
    is, in my humble opinion, the most efficient Java developement
    environment. It includes the most useful features of better Java
    tools (such as on the fly syntax checks, efficient code completion
    and a fast debugger), but without unnecessary fat, with makes it
    very fast (some of my colleagues though it was a native tool
    :o)</p>

   <figure url="codeguide-tips.codeguide.png">
    <title>CodeGuide IDE</title>
   </figure>

   <p>It is possible to extend CodeGuide features using external
    tools. CVS is integrated this way in the IDE for instance. In this
    article, I show how you can integrate JUnit, Beanshell and Ant as
    external tools.</p>

  </sect>

  <sect><title>JUnit integration</title>

   <p>JUnit is a well known unit test framework. Using this tool,
    developing and running these tests is a piece of cake. A dedicated
    Ant task may also generate test reports. JUnit is an Open Source
    tool that you can download for free at <link
    url="http://www.junit.org"/>. I have written an introduction to
    JUnit, in the May/June issue of <link
    url="http://otn.oracle.com/oramag/oracle/03-may/o33junit.html">Oracle
    Magazine</link>.</p>

   <p>The goal of this integration is to run a unit test, within
    CodeGuide, with a single click and see the result in the tools
    console.</p>

   <p>Open the <keyb>Tools/Configure Tools...</keyb> menu. The
    following dialog box will open:</p>

   <figure url="codeguide-tips.junit-dialog.png">
    <title>JUnit integration in CodeGuide</title>
   </figure>

   <p>Click on the <imp>New</imp> button and fill fields with the
    following values:</p>

   <table>
    <th>
     <co>Field</co>
     <co>Value</co>
     <co>Comment</co>
    </th>
    <li>
     <co>Category</co>
     <co> </co>
     <co>Leave this field empty (or the JUnit item would appear in a
      JUnit submenu, which is useless in this case).</co>
    </li>
    <li>
     <co>Name</co>
     <co>JUnit</co>
     <co>Logical</co>
    </li>
    <li>
     <co>Kind</co>
     <co>Tool for files</co>
     <co>To launch a Java source file as a JUnit test</co>
    </li>
    <li>
     <co>Console</co>
     <co>JUnit</co>
     <co>This is the name of the console which will display the result
      of the test</co>
    </li>
    <li>
     <co>Executable</co>
     <co>java</co>
     <co>We launch the <keyb>java</keyb> command</co>
    </li>
    <li>
     <co>Working directory</co>
     <co>$DESTINATION_DIRECTORY_PATH$</co>
     <co>To launch JUnit in the compilation destination directory</co>
    </li>
    <li>
     <co>Arguments</co>
     <co>-cp $CLASSPATH$ junit.textui.TestRunner $FILE_CLASSNAME$</co>
     <co>So that the launcher runs the Java class generated from the
      edited Java source file</co>
    </li>
    <li>
     <co>File pattern</co>
     <co>*Test.java</co>
     <co>We filter JUnit test cases</co>
    </li>
    <li>
     <co>Behavior</co>
     <co>Default</co>
     <co>Why not...</co>
    </li>
   </table>
   
   <p>Close the tool configuration dialog box clicking the
    <keyb>OK</keyb> button. You can now launch a test with a right
    click on a Java source file (in the <imp>project</imp> pane or in
    the editor itself) and selecting the <imp>JUnit</imp> item in the
    menu.</p>

   <figure url="codeguide-tips.junit-menu.png">
    <title>Run a JUnit test</title>
   </figure>

   <p>The test result appears in the tools console:</p>

   <figure url="codeguide-tips.junit-result.png">
    <title>JUnit test result</title>
   </figure>

   <p>Note that you must click on the <imp>Build Project</imp> button
    in the tool bar (or press key <imp>F9</imp>) before running a
    test, in order to build the corresponding class file. Furthermore,
    it is possible to launch a unit test using a <code>main()</code>
    method and changing the starting point of the project, but it is
    more convenient using the JUnit launcher (especially for web
    application where starting point is a bit weird).</p>
   
  </sect>

  <sect><title>Beanshell integration</title>

   <p>Beanshell is a Java interpreter (with some scripting
    features). You can download it for free at <link
     url="http://www.beanshell.org"/>. Integration in an IDE is useful
    when developing scripts or to test code fragments using the
    Beanshell interpreter as a scrap book.</p>

   <p>Thus, the goal of this integration is to run scripts from the
    editor and launch a Beanshell console.</p>

   <sect><title>Beanshell interpreter</title>

    <p>To integrate the script interpreter, open the tool
     configuration dialog box, click on the <imp>New</imp> button and
     fill the fields with the following values:</p>

    <table>
     <th>
      <co>Field</co>
      <co>Value</co>
      <co>Comment</co>
     </th>
     <li>
      <co>Category</co>
      <co> </co>
      <co>Leave this field empty</co>
     </li>
     <li>
      <co>Name</co>
      <co>Beanshell Interpreter</co>
      <co>Logical</co>
     </li>
     <li>
      <co>Kind</co>
      <co>Tool for files</co>
      <co>To interpret Beanshell sources</co>
     </li>
     <li>
      <co>Console</co>
      <co>Beanshell</co>
      <co>The name of this concole</co>
     </li>
     <li>
      <co>Executable</co>
      <co>java</co>
      <co>We run the <keyb>java</keyb> command</co>
     </li>
     <li>
      <co>Working directory</co>
      <co>$PARENT_DIRECTORY_PATH$</co>
      <co>We run a script within its directory</co>
     </li>
     <li>
      <co>Arguments</co>
      <co>-cp /opt/java/bsh/lib/bsh-1.2b7.jar:$CLASSPATH$
       bsh.Interpreter $FILE_PATH$</co>
      <co>We include the Beanshell's jar file in the CLASSPATH (change
       this path for your Beanshell installation directory) and we add
       the project's CLASSPATH, we pass the file to interpret as
       parameter</co>
     </li>
     <li>
      <co>File pattern</co>
      <co>*.bsh</co>
      <co>To select Beanshell source files</co>
     </li>
     <li>
      <co>Behavior</co>
      <co>Default</co>
      <co>Why not...</co>
     </li>
    </table>

    <p>We can now run the interpreter with a single right click on a
     script source and see the output in the Beanshell console.</p>

    <figure url="codeguide-tips.beanshell-interpreter.png">
     <title>Beanshell interpreter</title>
    </figure>

   </sect>

   <sect><title>Beanshell console</title>

    <p>To run the interpreter in a console, open the tool
     configuration dialog box, click on the <imp>New</imp> button, and
     fill the fields with the following values:</p>

    <table>
     <th>
      <co>Field</co>
      <co>Value</co>
      <co>Comment</co>
     </th>
     <li>
      <co>Category</co>
      <co> </co>
      <co>Leave this field empty</co>
     </li>
     <li>
      <co>Name</co>
      <co>Beanshell Console</co>
      <co>Logical</co>
     </li>
     <li>
      <co>Kind</co>
      <co>Tool in menu</co>
      <co>To lauch the interpreter from the <imp>Tools</imp> menu</co>
     </li>
     <li>
      <co>Console</co>
      <co>Beanshell</co>
      <co>The name of the console</co>
     </li>
     <li>
      <co>Executable</co>
      <co>java</co>
      <co>We run the Java virtual machine</co>
     </li>
     <li>
      <co>Working directory</co>
      <co> </co>
      <co>Leave empty (except if you want to work in a given
       directory)</co>
     </li>
     <li>
      <co>Arguments</co>
      <co>-cp /opt/java/bsh/lib/bsh-1.2b7.jar:$CLASSPATH$ bsh.Interpreter</co>
      <co>We add the Beanshell's jar file to the CLASSPATH (replace
       with the path for your Beanshell installation directory) and we
       append the CLASSPATH of the project. No file is passed on the
       command line so that the interpreter runs the user's
       inputs.</co>
     </li>
     <li>
      <co>File pattern</co>
      <co> </co>
      <co>Leave empty, has no meaning in this context</co>
     </li>
     <li>
      <co>Behavior</co>
      <co>Default</co>
      <co>Why not...</co>
     </li>
    </table>

    <p>To open the Beanshell console, select the <keyb>Tools/Beanshell
      Console</keyb> item of the menu, the following window appears:</p>

    <figure url="codeguide-tips.beanshell-console.png">
     <title>Beanshell console</title>
    </figure>

    <p>We can evaluate Java expressions and see the result in the
     console. This is an handy way to quickly test a piece of code and
     paste it in the editor.</p>

   </sect>

  </sect>

  <sect><title>Ant integration</title>

   <p>Ant is a build tool (that may be compared to make) dedicated to
    build Java projects. I have written a series of articles on Ant in
    the November/December and January/February issues of <link
    url="http://otn.oracle.com/oramag/oracle/02-nov/o62odev_ant.html">Oracle
    Magazine</link>. Ant is integrated to CodeGuide out of the box,
    but if you chose ant builds, on the fly code generation is not
    running, which is a key feature of CodeGuide.</p>

   <p>The goal of this integration is to launch an Ant build from
    within the interface using on the fly code compilation.</p>

   <p>Open the tool configuration dialog box and fill the fields as
    following:</p>

   <table>
    <th>
     <co>Field</co>
     <co>Value</co>
     <co>Comment</co>
    </th>
    <li>
     <co>Category</co>
     <co> </co>
     <co>Leave this field empty</co>
    </li>
    <li>
     <co>Name</co>
     <co>Ant</co>
     <co>No comment</co>
    </li>
    <li>
     <co>Kind</co>
     <co>Tool for files</co>
     <co>So that Ant looks in parents directories of the file you
      click (this works great if the build file is in the root
      directory of the project)</co>
    </li>
    <li>
     <co>Console</co>
     <co>Ant</co>
     <co>The name of the console</co>
    </li>
    <li>
     <co>Executable</co>
     <co>ant</co>
     <co>We run Ant</co>
    </li>
    <li>
     <co>Working directory</co>
     <co>$PARENT_DIRECTORY_PATH$</co>
     <co>We run Ant in the directory of the file</co>
    </li>
    <li>
     <co>Arguments</co>
     <co>-find build.xml $USER_ARGUMENTS$</co>
     <co>We ask Ant to look for a build file named
      <file>build.xml</file> recursively in parent directories. The
      value <value>$USER_ARGUMENTS$</value> gives the user a chance to
      type an Ant target to run</co>
    </li>
    <li>
     <co>File pattern</co>
     <co>*</co>
     <co>We can click on any file to launch an Ant build (useful to
      transform XML files using Ant builds for instance)</co>
    </li>
    <li>
     <co>Behavior</co>
     <co>Default</co>
     <co>Why not...</co>
    </li>
   </table>

   <p>You can now open a file context menu (with a right click) and
    launch the build choosing the Ant item. I genrally choose <imp>Use
     internal incremental compiler</imp> in my projects preferences
    and launch Ant builds when necessary (to generate a jar file for
    instance).</p>
   
    <figure url="codeguide-tips.ant.png">
     <title>Ant console displaying a build result</title>
    </figure>

  </sect>

  <sect><title>Conclusion</title>

   <p>Even if CodeGuide's customization can't compete with Emacs, it
    is very useful to integrate in this IDE your favorite tools. We
    could wonder what is missing to CodeGuide (when you'll have tested
    classes <term>Hot Swap</term> or Tomcat integration). Maybe a
    plugin API so that any developer could send Omnicore their own
    extensions. Please Omnicore developers, think about that!</p>

  </sect>

  <p>Thanks Frédéric for his corrections!</p>

 </text>

</article>

<!-- Local IspellDict: francais -->
