<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//SWEETOHM//DTD article 1.0//EN"
                         "../dtd/article.dtd">

<article author="Michel CASABIANCA"
         email="casa@sweetohm.net"
         date="2004-01-06"
         id="codeguide-antconsole.en"
         lang="en"
         keywords="codeguide, ant, console">

 <title>Fast Ant builds with CodeGuide</title>

 <abstract>
  <p>This article presents the integration of the Ant Console within
   CodeGuide to boost significantly build times. For Ant integration
   and other CodeGuide tips, see 
   <link url="codeguide-tips.en.html">this article</link>.</p>
 </abstract>

 <text>

  <sect><title>Ant Console</title>

   <p>This tool runs Ant in a console (in a terminal or within your
    favorite IDE) and lets you type commands to run targets of the
    loaded build file. This method runs much faster than Ant because
    it saves time to launch the Java Virtual Machine, JIT compilation
    time and build file loading. You can run builds up to 5 times
    faster than running Ant on the command line. It is obvious than
    you save more time on small builds (when time spent in usefull
    code is small compared to startup time).</p>

   <sect><title>Installation</title>

    <p>Download SAT that you can get for free <link
      url="http://www.cafebabe.net/html/sat.en.html">on my web
      site</link>.</p>

    <p>Go in the <file>bin</file> directory of your Ant installation,
     copy the <file>ant</file> script (or <file>ant.bat</file> for OS
     disabled people) to file <file>antc</file> (or
     <file>antc.bat</file>). Replace
     <code>org.apache.tools.ant.Main</code> with
     <code>net.cafebabe.sat.ant.Console</code>. This script will
     launch the Ant console instead of traditional Ant. Make sure that
     this script is in your <code>PATH</code>.</p>

    <p>You must,  of course, install SAT by dropping the file
     <file>sat.jar</file> in the <file>lib</file> directory of your
     Ant installation.</p>

   </sect>

   <sect><title>Usage</title>

    <p>To run the Ant console, go in the directory of your project
     (where is living your <file>build.xml</file> file) ant type
     <keyb>antc</keyb>. You will display an help screen typing
     <keyb>antc -help</keyb> on the command line&dp;</p>

<source><![CDATA[Ant Console 0.8 (C) Michel Casabianca 2003
type "help" to get help on console commands
Usage: antc [-help] [-version] [-timer] [-file file] [-find file]
-help    Print this help screen
-version Print the version
-timer   Print build times
-file    To set the build file
-find    To search for the build file]]></source>


    <p>When you launch the Ant console, you will be promped as
     following&dp;</p>

    <figure url="codeguide-antconsole.console.png">
     <title>Ant Console running</title>
    </figure>

    <p>To display an help screen about the console commands, type
     <keyb>help</keyb> in the console&dp;</p>

<source><![CDATA[Commands you can run in the console are the following:
  help          To display this help screen
  exit          To quit the console                                     
  desc          To describe the loaded project
  load file     To load the build file
  find file     To find the project file
  reload        To reload the current project
  timer on/off  To set timer on/off
  target foo    To run the target foo
  targetname    To run the target (can't be a console command)
  <empty>       To repeat the last command]]></source>

    <p>Note that you can launch a given target by typing its name
     (this is a shortcut for the <keyb>target</keyb> command) provided
     that this target hasn't the same name than a console command. You
     can repeat the last command by typing <keyb>ENTER</keyb>.</p>

    <p>You can load a build file using the <keyb>load</keyb>
     command (the path is then relative to the current directory) and
     search for a build file recursively in the file system with the
     <keyb>find</keyb> command (that behaves like the
     <keyb>-find</keyb> command line argument for Ant). You can also
     reload the current project with <keyb>reload</keyb>. This may be
     necessary when the build file  changes on disk or when the
     project is corrupted (which happens sometimes after a build error
     because some tasks don't work after an error).</p>

    <p>The <keyb>desc</keyb> command describes the current project
     (behaves like the <keyb>-projecthelp</keyb> command line
     parameter for Ant).</p>

    <p>I have also implemented a timer (to display execution time for
     builds) that you can switch <value>on</value> or
     <value>off</value> using the <keyb>timer</keyb> command. The
     result is in milliseconds (because the builds are so fast :o)</p>

   </sect>

  </sect>

  <sect><title>Integration in CodeGuide</title>

   <p>I have <link url="codeguide-tips.en.html">already said</link>
    that this IDE is fast and probably the most powerful for real
    world Java development, Ant is very slow compared to this
    tool. The goal of this integration is to make Ant run at light
    speed in CodeGuide.</p>

   <p>First, make sure that the Ant Console runs properly from the
    command line (by typing <keyb>antc</keyb> in a terminal). Then we
    will integrate it as an external tool. To do so, open
    <imp>Tools/Configure tools...</imp> in the menu. The following
    window opens to let you configure an external tool:</p>

   <figure url="codeguide-antconsole.configure-tools.png">
    <title>Tools configuration window</title>
   </figure>

   <p>Click on the <imp>New</imp> button and fill fields with the
    following values:</p>

   <table>
    <th>
     <co>Field</co>
     <co>Value</co>
     <co>Comment</co>
    </th>
    <li>
     <co>Category</co>
     <co> </co>
     <co>Leave this field empty (or the Ant Concole item would appear
      in a submenu, which is useless in this case).</co>
    </li>
    <li>
     <co>Name</co>
     <co>Ant Console</co>
     <co>Logical</co>
    </li>
    <li>
     <co>Kind</co>
     <co>Tool for files</co>
     <co>To run the console searching for the build file recursively
      in the file system</co>
    </li>
    <li>
     <co>Console</co>
     <co>Ant Console</co>
     <co>As the tool is running in the background, it should run in
      its own console (don't run it in the Ant console for instance
      because you wold have to stop it to launch a regular build)</co>
    </li>
    <li>
     <co>Executable</co>
     <co>antc</co>
     <co>We launch the <keyb>antc</keyb> command</co>
    </li>
    <li>
     <co>Working directory</co>
     <co>$PARENT_DIRECTORY_PATH$</co>
     <co>To launch the console it the directory of the file</co>
    </li>
    <li>
     <co>Arguments</co>
     <co>-find build.xml</co>
     <co>The console look for the build file in the file system (so
      that if we launch the console on a Java source file, it will
      search for the build file in a parent directory)</co>
    </li>
    <li>
     <co>File pattern</co>
     <co>*</co>
     <co>We can launch the console on any file (I use it to perform my
      XSLT transformations for instance, so I run it on XML files for
      instance)</co>
    </li>
    <li>
     <co>Behavior</co>
     <co>Default</co>
     <co>Why not...</co>
    </li>
   </table>

   <p>To run the console, right click on a file (in the ditor pane or
    in the <imp>Project</imp> bar) and select the item <imp>Ant
    Console</imp>.</p>

   <figure url="codeguide-antconsole.menu.png">
    <title>Launch the Ant Console on a file</title>
   </figure>

   <p>This will open a dedicated console where Ant is waiting for your
    commands. Take a look at the build times (in milliseconds), it
    screams!</p>

   <figure url="codeguide-antconsole.codeguide-console.png">
    <title>The Ant Console running in CodeGuide</title>
   </figure>

   <p>The same build using Ant takes about 6 seconds (about 4 times
    more). Using the latest PowerMac dual G5 2GHz, you could probably
    compete for the fastest Ant builds on earth :o)</p>

  </sect>

  <p>Thanks Frédéric for his corrections</p>

  <p>Enjoy!</p>

 </text>

</article>

<!-- Local IspellDict: english -->
