<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//CAFEBABE//DTD article 1.0//EN"
                         "../dtd/article.dtd">

<article lang="en"
         id="fiji.doc.en"
         date="2003-01-12"
         email="casa@sweetohm.net"
         author="Michel CASABIANCA"
         keywords="java, installer">
 
 <title>FiJI 1.0-1</title>

 <abstract>
  <p>FiJI is a Free Java Installer released under GPL.</p>
 </abstract>

 <text>

  <sect><title>Installing FiJI</title>

   <p>To install FiJI, you must first install a 1.2 or 1.3 Java Virtual
    Machine. You can download one for free on
    <link url="http://java.sun.com/products/jdk/1.2">Sun's web site</link>.
   </p>

   <p>The latest version of FiJI is on
    <link url="http://www.sweetohm.net/html/fiji.html">my web
     page</link>. To install it, go to the directory where you saved the
    archive and type <code>java -jar fiji-0.4.jar</code>. Windows and Solaris
    users can simply double-click the file. FiJI is delivered with himself
    has a self extracting installer, so you should have an idea of what
    it can do.</p>

   <p><imp>Note:</imp> Windows may complain that it doesn't have enough
    environment space. In this case, add the line <code>shell=command.com
     /E:8000 /P</code> to your <file>config.sys</file> file and reboot.
    Furthermore, the environment should not alter file names, there is
    an option under Windows NT to work with case sensitive file names.</p>

  </sect>

  <sect><title>Building FiJI</title>

   <p>To build FiJI, you will need Ant version 1.2. You can download it on
     <link url="http://jakarta.apache.org/ant">Apache web site</link>.
    Simply type <code>ant</code> in the install directory to rebuild.</p>

  </sect>

  <sect><title>Using FiJI</title>

   <p>Let's have a look on the <file>install.xml</file> file in the install
    directory of FiJI :</p>

<source>&lt;?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?&gt;

&lt;install jar="/tmp/fiji-0.4.jar"
         logo="lib/logo.gif"&gt;
    &lt;text title="FiJI"
          text="This program will install Fiji on\
                your computer. Hit [|&gt;] to continue\
                or [O] to abort installation."/&gt;
    &lt;license file="lib/LICENSE"/&gt;
    &lt;copy dir="tmp"
          property="fiji.home"
          defaults="Windows=c:\Fiji,Unix=/usr/local/fiji"&gt;
          &lt;filter file="bin/fiji" from="@HOME@" to="${fiji.home}"/&gt;
          &lt;filter file="bin/fiji.bat" from="@HOME@" to="${fiji.home}"/&gt;
    &lt;/copy&gt;
    &lt;link from="${fiji.home}/bin/fiji"
          to="/usr/local/bin"
          mandatory="no"/&gt;
    &lt;append file="c:\autoexec.bat"
            line="set PATH=%PATH%;${fiji.home}\bin"
            os="Windows"
            mandatory="no"/&gt;
    &lt;text title="Congratulation !"
          text="FiJI have been installed succesfully.\
                Hit [O] to terminate this program."/&gt;
&lt;/install&gt;</source>

   <p>This XML file is a script for the installation. Each element
    is a screen of the installer:</p>

   <enum>
    <item>The first screen (<file>text</file> element) shows a welcome message.
     This message is written in the <file>text</file> attribute of this
     element.</item>
    <item>Then the user must agree the license (in the <file>license</file>
     element). The path to the license file is in the <file>file</file>
     attribute.</item>
    <item>The third screen (<file>copy</file> element) asks for an installation
     directory and copies files in that directory.</item>
    <item>Then, if the user is running a Unix box, it will be prompt for
     a destination directory (in his <file>PATH</file>) for a link to the
     script launching the application.</item>
    <item>If the user is installing the program on Windows, the next
     screen will append a line to his <file>autoexec.bat</file> file
     (to put the <file>bin</file> directory in the <file>PATH</file>).</item>
    <item>The program ends the installation with another message that
     informs the user that the installation was successful.</item>
   </enum>

   <p>As you can see, this script is quite simple and easy to code
    (few minutes when you know the syntax of these elements). To
    produce the installation Jar file, simply go the directory of
    the script and type <code>fiji</code>. You can indicate
    the location of the script on the command line and specify a
    verbosity argument (<code>-v</code>). Type <code>fiji -help</code> for a
    short help on the command line arguments.</p>

   <p>To run the installer, the user will have to go the the directory
    where he saved the Jar file, and type : <code>java -jar
     archive-name.jar</code>, or double click it (on Windows or Solaris).</p>

  </sect>

  <sect><title>FiJI Tasks</title>

   <p>The elements of the install file are tasks (except for the
    root element and filters). The root element, <file>install</file>
    can accept two attributes :</p>

<source>
  &lt;install jar="../fiji-0.3.jar"
           logo="lib/logo.gif"&gt;
  ...
  &lt;/install&gt;
</source>

   <p>The first one, <file>jar</file> names the produced Jar installer.
    The second gives the URL of the logo (the picture on the left of
    the frame). This attribute is not mandatory (no image is dispayed
    if this attribute is missing).</p>

   <p>You can customize the installer interface with the <file>theme</file>
    element (that comes just after <file>install</file> one). It may
    have up to six attributes (<file>primary1</file>,
    <file>primary2</file>, <file>primary3</file>, <file>secondary1</file>,
    <file>secondary2</file> and <file>secondary3</file>) that define a hexadecimal
    coded color. Those six colors define a theme for Swing(Metal look
    &amp; feel), as defined
    <link url="http://java.sun.com/products/jlf/dg/higg.htm">
     on this page page</link>. For instance, the following element
    defines the theme for the FiJI installer:</p>

   <source>    &lt;theme primary2="6eb2ce"
           primary3="d5fedc"/&gt;</source>

   <p>In order the install script to be fully portable, the paths
    must be written in the URL notation (Unix paths). Just replace
    under Windows the antislash with slash. Thus, you would
    write <file>foo/bar.txt</file> instead of <file>foo\bar.txt</file>.
    Furthermore, relative paths are relative to the directory
    of the <file>install.xml</file> script.</p>

   <p>Each screen of the installer is processed by a specific task.
    Those tasks are :</p>

   <sect><title>Text</title>

    <p>This task shows a simple text (in the <file>text</file> attribute)
     with a title (in the <file>title</file> attribute). For instance:</p>

<source>
    &lt;text title="FiJI"
          text="This program will install Fiji on\
                your computer. Hit [&gt;] to continue\
                or [O] to abort installation."/&gt;
</source>

    <p>Produces the screen:</p>

    <figure url="fiji.text.png" width="10"/>

    <p>This is the first screen of the installer for FiJI itself. Those
     two attributes are mandatory. A new line is indicated with
     an antislash.</p>

   </sect>

   <sect><title>License</title>

    <p>This task displays a license for agreement. The user must
     agree (by clicking on the message <file>I accept the terms of this
      License</file>) this license or abort installation. For instance:</p>

<source>
    &lt;license file="lib/LICENSE"/&gt;
</source>

    <p>Displays the screen:</p>

    <figure url="fiji.license.png" width="10"/>

    <p>This element displays the license in the text file <file>LICENSE</file> in
     the <file>lib</file> subdirectory (all paths are relative to the directory
     of the <file>install.xml</file> script, except for absolute ones, starting
     with "/").</p>

   </sect>

   <sect><title>Copy</title>

    <p>This task installs the content of a directory (the one of the
     application to install) in a directory chosen by the user. This
     directory is ziped when the archive is being built.</p>

<source>
    &lt;copy dir="tmp"
          property="fiji.home"
          defaults="Windows=c:\Fiji,Unix=/usr/local/fiji"&gt;
          &lt;filter file="bin/fiji" from="@HOME@"
                  to="${fiji.home}"/&gt;
          &lt;filter file="bin/fiji.bat" from="@HOME@"
                  to="${fiji.home}"/&gt;
    &lt;/copy&gt;
</source>

    <p>Displays the following screen:</p>

    <figure url="fiji.copy.png" width="10"/>

    <p>The <file>dir</file> attribute indicates the source directory to
     copy. <file>property</file> gives to the program the property name for
     the installation directory. You can use this property in other
     tasks. For instance, the attribute <file>to</file> of the element
     <file>filter</file> is <file>${fiji.home}</file>, so it will be replaced
     with the installation directory. The last attribute, <file>defaults</file>
     indicates a list of default install dirs with their targeted
     plateform.</p>

    <p>The <file>filter</file> elements can be nested within <file>copy</file>
     ones. They are usefull to filter some given files. For instance,
     the element :</p>

<source>
          &lt;filter file="bin/fiji" from="@HOME@"
                  to="${fiji.home}"/&gt;
</source>

    <p>Will filter the file <file>bin/fiji</file> (of the directory,
     <file>after</file> installation), replacing the string <code>@HOME@</code> with
     <code>${fiji.home}</code>, which is the installation directory
     (which name is given by the <file>property</file> attribute of
     the <file>copy</file> element). Thus, the following script:</p>

<source>
  #!/bin/sh
  java -jar @HOME@/fiji.jar -v "$@"
</source>

    <p>Will be replaced (after the filter applies) by:</p>

<source>
  #!/bin/sh
  java -jar /usr/local/fiji/fiji.jar -v "$@"
</source>

    <p>On the user's hard disk, if he chosed <file>/usr/local/fiji</file>
     as installation directory (the default install dir for Unix).</p>


    <p>When the user clicks on the <imp>[&gt;]</imp> button, the files
     will be copied and the progress bar shows the progression.</p>

   </sect>

   <sect><title>Link</title>

    <p>This task is specific to Unix systems (and won't be processed on
     other systems). Let's consider the following element:</p>

<source>
    &lt;link from="${fiji.home}/bin/fiji" to="/usr/local/bin"/&gt;
</source>

    <p>It will display the screen:</p>

    <figure url="fiji.link.png" width="10"/>

    <p>This task will perform two things :</p>

    <enum>
     <item>It will make the file <file>${fiji.home}/bin/fiji</file>
      (the launching script) runnable (with
      <code>chmod a+rx ${fiji.home}/bin/fiji</code>).</item>
     <item>It will make a symlink from this file to the directory
      the user choosed (the default value is <file>/usr/local/bin</file>),
      that is supposed to be in the <file>PATH</file> of the user, with
      <code>ln -sf ${fiji.home}/bin/fiji /usr/local/bin</code>.</item>
    </enum>

    <p>The user can now type <code>fiji</code> on the command line to
     launch FiJI.</p>

   </sect>

   <sect><title>KDE Desktop</title>

    <p>This task is for Unix systems running the KDE window manager (and
     will not be processed on other systems). Let's consider the
     following element:</p>

<source>
    &lt;kdeDesktop exec="fiji"
                icon="${fiji.home}/prj/fiji/lib/fiji.gif"
                term="1"/&gt;
</source>

    <p>It will display the screen:</p>

    <figure url="fiji.kde.png" width="10"/>

    <p>This task prompts for adding an icon on the desktop of the
     user to launch the application. The <file>exec</file> attribute
     indicates the command line to launch the application.
     <file>icon</file> is the path to the icon file (on the system
     where the program have been installed). <file>term</file> indicates
     if the program must be launched in a terminal (<file>1</file> value)
     or not (<file>0</file> value).</p>

   </sect>

   <sect><title>File update</title>

    <p>This task append a line to a given file. It is useful to update
     a configuration file (such as <file>autoexec.bat</file> or
     <file>/etc/profile</file>). The corresponding element is:</p>

    <source>    &lt;append file="c:\autoexec.bat"
            line="set PATH=%PATH%;${fiji.home}\bin"
            os="Windows"/&gt;</source>

    <p>This element will display the following screen:</p>

    <figure url="fiji.append.png" width="10"/>

    <p>This task displays the line (in the attribute <file>line</file>) to
     append to a file which default name is in <file>file</file> attribute.
     The <file>os</file> attribute indicates the target OS.</p>

   </sect>

   <sect><title>Common attributes for all tasks</title>

    <p>All tasks accept the following attributes:</p>

    <list>
     <item><imp>mandatory</imp> (<file>yes</file> or <file>no</file> values)
      indicates if this task is mandatory (any task defaults to
      mandatory). If it is not, the user can click on the [&gt;&gt;] button
      to skip this task. If a task is mandatory, this button is
      disabled.</item>
     <item><imp>title</imp> gives the title for the task (see the <file>text</file>
      task for more details).</item>
     <item><imp>text</imp> is the same than <file>title</file> but for the text
      of the task. For the <file>license</file> task, it indicates the
      text to accept the license. The <file>link</file> tasks can take a
      second text for the second line of the screen. This text is set
      with the <file>text2</file> attribute.</item>
     <item><imp>error</imp> is used to set the error text for some tasks
      that may display some. This is the case for <file>license</file>
      task (if the user did not accept the license) and <file>kdeDesktop</file>
      (error when creating the shortcut). Some tasks can have two error
      messages: <file>copy</file> (error creating the installation directory
      and copying files) and <file>link</file> (error changing mode and
      making the link). The second error message is set using the
      <file>error2</file> attribute.</item>
    </list>

    <p>Those attributes make it possible to customize the interface
     but also to translate the installer.</p>

   </sect>

  </sect>

  <sect><title>How it works</title>

   <p>To explain the principles of this program, we must consider two
    stages : the generation of the Jar installer and the extraction
    performed by the installer.</p>

   <p>The builder generates the installer (that is a Jar file) this
    way :</p>

   <enum>
    <item>The xml builder (class <file>casa.fiji.builder.XmlBuilder</file>)
     reads the XML file (<file>install.xml</file>) and builds an object
     tree while processing elements. It uses reflection (and doesn't
     know anything about the generated objects). When it encounters
     a <file>foo</file> element, it instanciates a <file>Foo</file> object.
     When it encounters a <file>bar</file> attribute, it calls a method
     named <file>setBar()</file> with the value of the attribute on the
     parent element. When an element <file>bar</file> is nested within
     an element <file>foo</file>, it calls a method <file>add</file> on the
     object <file>Foo</file> with <file>Bar</file> as argument.</item>
    <item>The main class of the builder (<file>casa.fiji.builder.Main</file>)
     collects the resources needed by the classes involved in the installer
     and put them in the Jar file (that will be the installer itself).</item>
    <item>Then the <file>casa.fiji.installer.Install</file> class (the
     main class of the installer, generated by the XML builder) is
     serialized and placed in the Jar installer. It coutains references
     to the other classes of the installer, that are this way serialized
     too.</item>
   </enum>

   <p>This method is a simple way to configure the classes of the
    installer. Their configuration is performed by the XML builder by
    calling their methods <file>setFoo()</file>. Furthermore, this
    methods is light : the serialized classes weight less than 1000
    compressed bytes, that is far less than the weight of the XML file
    itself (and if I used an XML parser to configure the installer, I
    would have to carry the parser in the archive).</p>

   <p>I have been told that there could be problems between versions
    of serialized classes, but I had no problems during my tests (with
    1.1, 1.2 and 1.3 virtual machines).</p>

   <p>The second stage (extraction of the archive) works this way :</p>

   <enum>
    <item>When you lauch the Jar file, the <file>main()</file> method of the
     main class of the installer (<file>casa.fiji.installer.Install</file>)
     is called. This class deserializes itself, obtaining the serialized
     data in the Jar file. The object tree of the installer is then
     rebuilt.</item>
    <item>This class selects the apropriate tasks (calling the methods
     <file>isValid()</file> of each task in the stack). A task can be valid
     for a given OS or if a given directory exists for instance.</item>
    <item>Then the installer calls the <file>init()</file> and <file>done()</file>
     method of the tasks as the user view them.</item>
    <item>A task performs its work in the <file>done()</file> method that
     is called by the installer when the user clicks the <imp>[&gt;]</imp>
     button. If it does something quick (that doesn't cause CPU starvation),
     it return <file>true</file>, indicating to the installer that the work
     is done. If a task takes a long time (such as copying many files),
     it returns <file>false</file>. When the work is done, it calls the
     method <file>update()</file> of the installer to indicate that to work
     is done.</item>
   </enum>

   <p>This text is a rapid overview of the builder and the installer,
    dig the code for more details (without comments, sorry ;o).</p>

  </sect>

  <sect><title>How to develop new tasks for FiJI</title>

   <p>FiJI is an extensible system: it is possible to develop new
    tasks to meet your specific needs. I will take as example the
    <code>Link</code> task that makes a link (for Unix systems) from
    a script to a directory in the <file>PATH</file>.</p>

   <sect><title>XML element</title>

    <p>To make such a link, you must know the source file and
     target directory. Thus, the element for this task will be
     the following:</p>

    <source>
    &lt;link from="${fiji.home}/bin/fiji" to="/usr/local/bin"/&gt;
    </source>

    <p>The <file>link</file> element gives the name of the class to
     develop (<code>Link</code> with an uppercase in order to follow the
     Java naming conventions). The <file>from</file> attribute gives the
     name of the source file while <file>to</file> indicates the target
     directory for the link.</p>

   </sect>

   <sect><title>Initialisation de l'installeur</title>

    <p>When the FiJI XML parser encounters such an element, it tries
     to instantiate the <code>Link</code> class, the invokes the
     <code>setFrom()</code> and <code>setTo()</code> methods on it. The FiJI
     task system is extensible because the program knows nothing about
     the tasks it builds, but uses reflexion instead. Thus, it is not
     necessary to modify FiJI's source code to add new tasks.</p>

    <p>Furthermore, hour class must extend the abstract class
     <code>casa.fiji.installer.Task</code> in order to be a valid task.
     It must also live in the <code>casa.fiji.installer</code> package.</p>

    <p>To finish about tasks, I have to talk about the resources and
     classes to add in the installer file. Because this file must contain
     all the necessary classes and resources to run, you must indicate
     those in the <file>install.xml</file> file.</p>

    <p>Task classes are automatically added (using reflexion) by the
     <code>Task</code> class: it adds the class for the task and the GUI
     (which name is the one of the class plus <file>UI</file>, so if the
     class for the task is called <code>Link</code>, the class for the GUI
     is called <code>LinkUI</code>) in the list of files to add in the
     archive. If your code uses another class, it must do so using
     the <code>addClass()</code> method in it's contructor and passing the
     list of qualified class names (with package) to this method.
     In our example, adding new classes in the archive is not necessary,
     so we don't have to call this method.</p>

    <p>If your task uses resources (such as an icon file), you declare
     it invoking the <code>addResources()</code> method, passing the list
     of files as argument. Note that the GUI reference is marqued
     <file>transient</file> because this GUI must not be serialized (as
     it is dangerous and useless to serialize this object).</p>

    <p>You know enought now to anderstand the first part of the class
     <code>Task</code> that is following:</p>

<source>
/*
 * This program is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
 * modify it under the terms of the GNU General Public License
 * as published by the Free Software Foundation; either version 2
 * of the License, or any later version.
 *
 * This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
 * but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
 * MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the
 * GNU General Public License for more details.
 *
 * You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License
 * along with this program; if not, write to the Free Software
 * Foundation, Inc., 59 Temple Place - Suite 330, Boston, MA  02111-1307, USA.
 */

package casa.fiji.installer;

import casa.fiji.util.Misc;
import java.awt.*;
import javax.swing.*;
import java.io.*;
import java.util.*;

/**
 * The link  task. It creates a link from a script (or executable) to a
 * directory in the PATH. For Unix systems only.
 */
public class Link extends Task {

    /**
     * The from part of the link.
     */
    String from=null;
    /**
     * The from part of the link, expanded.
     */
    String fromExpanded=null;
    /**
     * The to part of the link.
     */
    String to=null;
    /**
     * The to part of the link, expanded.
     */
    String toExpanded=null;
    /**
     * The reference to the GUI.
     */
    transient LinkUI ui=null;
    /**
     * The resources used by this task.
     */
    static final String[] resources={"lib/home.gif"};

    /**
     * Constructor. Adds resources to the jar installer.
     */
    public Link() {
        super();
        addResources(resources);
    }

    /**
     *Sets the from part of the link.
     */
    public void setFrom(String from) {this.from=from;}

    /**
     * Sets the to part of the link.
     */
    public void setTo(String to) {this.to=to;}
</source>

    <p>This first part is called when the installer archive is built
     (to initialize the <code>Link</code> task). All the tasks rely in
     a <code>Vector</code> in the <code>casa.fiji.install.Install</code> class
     (that is the main class of the installer). This object (and
     other tasks it contains) is serialized in the installer file.
     When running the installer, this object is deserialized and
     launched, which launches the install procedure.</p>

   </sect>

   <sect><title>Installer initialization</title>

    <p>We will now study the part of the code running at installation
     time.</p>

    <p>First, that installer must know if the task is to be runned
     on the host sytem (some tasks run only on given systems and/or
     configurations). To do so, it calls the <code>isValid()</code>
     method that returns a boolean. In our task, we simply return
     <file>true</file> if the system is Unix.</p>

    <p>Then, the installer must retrieve the task's GUI. It is done by
     calling the <code>getUI()</code> method. Our method simply instantiates
     a <code>LinkUI</code> object and returns it.</p>

    <p>Those methods are called during installer initialization. The
     following ones are called when the task is processed:</p>

    <p>The <code>init()</code> method is called when the task's GUI is
     shown. It evaluates the <file>from</file> and <file>to</file> expressions,
     that is, it replaces property references with their value. For
     instance, it will replace <file>${fiji.home}/bin/fiji</file> with
     <file>/usr/local/fiji/bin/fiji</file> if the installation directory
     is <file>/usr/local/fiji</file>. Note that the expanded values are
     stored in fields suffixed with <file>Expanded</file> in order
     another evaluation to remain possible if the user come back to
     a previous task.</p>

    <p>When the user clicks on the <imp>[&gt;]</imp> button (to call the
     next task), the installer calls the <code>next()</code> method of
     the current task. This method returns <file>true</file> if everything
     is OK and <file>false</file> if something went wrong during the
     operation. In this case, the next task is not shown.</p>

    <p>Here is the code for this part of the task:</p>

<source>
    /**
     * Indicates if the system running the installer should run this task.
     * That is if it is a Unix like system.
     */
    public boolean isValid() {
        return isUnix();
    }

    /**
     * Returns the GUI for this task.
     */
    public Component getUI() {
        ui=new LinkUI(this);
        return ui;
    }

    /**
     * Init is called when the task is shown in the installer. It expands
     * the from and to parts of the link (evaluating expressions).
     */
    public void init() {
        fromExpanded=Misc.expand(from);
        toExpanded=Misc.expand(to);
        ui.setFrom(fromExpanded);
        ui.setTo(toExpanded);
    }

    /**
     * Creates the link (when the user clicks on the next button).
     */
    public boolean next() {
        // build the chmod command
        toExpanded=ui.getTo();
        String command="chmod a+x "+fromExpanded;
        String error=Misc.execute(command);
        // if error, display an error message
        if(error!=null) {
            JOptionPane.showMessageDialog(ui,
                "Unbable to change the mode:\n"+command+'\n'+error,
                "Error",JOptionPane.ERROR_MESSAGE);
            return false;
        }
        // build the ln command
        command="ln -sf "+fromExpanded+" "+toExpanded;
        error=Misc.execute(command);
        // if error, display an error message
        if(error!=null) {
            JOptionPane.showMessageDialog(ui,
                "Unbable to make the link:\n"+command+'\n'+error,
                "Error",JOptionPane.ERROR_MESSAGE);
            return false;
        }
        return true;
    }
}
</source>

   </sect>

   <sect><title>Graphic Interface</title>

    <p>We must code a GUI for our task. This interface is implemented
     in the <code>LinkUI</code> class which source code is:</p>

<source>
/*
 * This program is free software; you can redistribute it and/or
 * modify it under the terms of the GNU General Public License
 * as published by the Free Software Foundation; either version 2
 * of the License, or any later version.
 *
 * This program is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
 * but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
 * MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE.  See the
 * GNU General Public License for more details.
 *
 * You should have received a copy of the GNU General Public License
 * along with this program; if not, write to the Free Software
 * Foundation, Inc., 59 Temple Place - Suite 330, Boston, MA  02111-1307, USA.
 */

package casa.fiji.installer;

import casa.fiji.util.Misc;
import java.io.*;
import java.awt.*;
import java.awt.event.*;
import javax.swing.*;

/**
 * The GUI for the link task.
 */
public class LinkUI extends JPanel implements ActionListener {

    /**
     * The refernce to the task.
     */
    Link link=null;
    /**
     * The text field for the directory.
     */
    JTextField field=new JTextField();
    /**
     * The label for the from part of the link.
     */
    JTextField label=new JTextField();
    /**
     * Home button.
     */
    JButton buttonHome=new JButton(new
        ImageIcon(ClassLoader.getSystemResource("lib/home.gif")));

    /**
     * The constructor. GUI initialization.
     */
    public LinkUI(Link link) {
        this.link=link;
        ui();
    }

    /**
     * GUI initialization.
     */
    void ui() {
        setLayout(new GridBagLayout());
        Misc.add(this,new JLabel("Link"), 0, 0, 2, 1, 0.0, 0.0,
		    GridBagConstraints.NORTH, GridBagConstraints.NONE,
		    new Insets(10, 10, 10, 10));
        Misc.add(this,new JLabel("This program will make a link from:"),
		    0, 1, 2, 1, 0.0, 1.0,GridBagConstraints.SOUTHWEST,
		    GridBagConstraints.NONE,new Insets(10, 10, 5, 10));
        Misc.add(this,label, 0, 2, 2, 1, 1.0, 0.0,
		    GridBagConstraints.SOUTHWEST, GridBagConstraints.HORIZONTAL,
		    new Insets(0, 10, 10, 10));
        Misc.add(this,new JLabel("to a directory in your PATH:"),
            0, 3, 2, 1, 0.0, 0.0,GridBagConstraints.NORTHWEST,
            GridBagConstraints.NONE,new Insets(10, 10, 5, 10));
        Misc.add(this,field, 0, 4, 1, 1, 1.0, 1.0,
            GridBagConstraints.NORTHWEST, GridBagConstraints.HORIZONTAL,
            new Insets(0, 10, 10, 5));
        Misc.add(this,buttonHome, 1, 4, 1, 1, 0.0, 1.0,
		    GridBagConstraints.NORTHEAST, GridBagConstraints.NONE,
		    new Insets(0, 0, 10, 10));
        buttonHome.addActionListener(this);
        buttonHome.setMargin(new Insets(0,0,0,0));
        label.setEditable(false);
    }

    /**
     * User actions processing.
     */
    public void actionPerformed(ActionEvent e) {
        if(e.getSource()==buttonHome) {
            JFileChooser chooser=new
                JFileChooser(System.getProperty("user.home"));
            chooser.setDialogType(JFileChooser.OPEN_DIALOG|
                JFileChooser.DIRECTORIES_ONLY);
            int returnVal=chooser.showOpenDialog(this);
            File dir=chooser.getCurrentDirectory();
            if(dir.isDirectory()) field.setText(dir.getAbsolutePath());
        }
    }

    /**
     * Sets the to part of the link.
     */
    public void setTo(String to) {field.setText(to);}

    /**
     * Returns the to part of the link.
     */
    public String getTo() {return field.getText();}

    /**
     * Sets the from part of the link.
     */
    public void setFrom(String from) {label.setText(from);}
}
</source>

    <p>This class is quite obvious except that it must extend
     (directly or not) <code>JPanel</code>. Note that it uses the
     <code>add()</code> method of <code>casa.fiji.util.Misc</code> class
     that adds a component to a <code>GridBagLayout</code>. Please
     don't code graphic interfaces using absolute coordinates
     for components (your code would not be portable).</p>

    <p>To use a task in FiJI, you must put the classes in the
     <file>CLASSPATH</file> to use it.</p>

    <p>I hope this overview is sufficient to start coding tasks.
     I think the best way to do so is to modify the example
     source code. Please feel free to contact me for any question.</p>

   </sect>

   <sect><title>Tasks License</title>

    <p>This program is under GPL, so any task should have the
     same license. Anyway, you might use this installer to
     distribute a program under any license (including
     commercial ones).</p>

   </sect>

  </sect>
  
  <sect><title>Ant task</title>

   <p>To use this task in a build file, you must drop the archive
    <file>fiji.jar</file> in the <file>lib</file> directory of your
    Ant installation.</p>

   <sect><title>Description</title>

    <p>Using this task, you can generate FiJI installers from within
     an Ant build file.</p>

     <p>The declarative element (after the
      <file>&lt;project&gt;</file> one) is the following:</p>

     <source>&lt;taskdef name="fiji" classname="net.cafebabe.fiji.builder.FijiTask"/&gt;</source>

    </sect>

    <sect><title>Parameters</title>

    <table>
     <th>
      <co>Attribute</co>
      <co>Description</co>
      <co>Required</co>
     </th>
     <li>
      <co>file</co>
      <co>Installer definition file.</co>
      <co>Yes</co>
     </li>
     <li>
      <co>verbose</co>
      <co>If <value>true</value>, messages are printed during
       installer generation.</co>
      <co>No (defaults to <value>no</value>)</co>
     </li>
     </table>

    </sect>

    <sect><title>Nested elements</title>

    <p>This task accepts no nested element or text.</p>
   
   </sect>

   <sect><title>Examples</title>

    <p>To generate an installer which definition file is
     <file>fiji/install.xml</file> in verbose mode, you might
     write&dp;</p>

    <source>&lt;fiji file="fiji/install.xml"
      verbose="true"/></source>

   </sect>

  </sect>

  <sect><title>License</title>

   <p>This software is free and released under the
    <link url="http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/gpl.html">GPL</link>.
    You can find a copy of this license in the file <file>LICENSE</file>
    in the installation directory.</p>

  </sect>

  <sect><title>History</title>
  
   <sect><title>Version 1.0-1 (2003-01-12)</title>

    <p>This version fixes a bug when loading XML configuration file
     (with a message "String index out of range: 1"). Many thanks to
     Daphné Costantini for this bug report. Also fixes a bug in the
     installer of the application.</p>
     
   </sect>

   <sect><title>Version 1.0 (2002-11-16)</title>

    <list>
     <item>New Ant task to generate FiJI installers.</item>
     <item>New package name (<code>net.cafebabe.fiji</code>).</item>
    </list>

   </sect>

   <sect><title>Version 0.4 (2000-12-31)</title>

    <list>
     <item>New <file>title</file>, <file>text</file> and <file>mandatory</file>
      for all elements.</item>
     <item>New <file>append</file> task that enable to update a configuration
      file.</item>
     <item>The [&gt;&gt;] button (to skip a task) and the task counter have
      been added to the interface.</item>
     <item>The installer interface may be customized using theme.</item>
    </list>

   </sect>

   <sect><title>Version 0.3 (2000-12-27)</title>

    <list>
     <item>This version have been heavily tested on Windows.</item>
     <item>Error management have been improved (exception stack
      traces have been replaced with clear messages, for instance,
      the program clearly indicates that it doesn't find the
      configuration file).</item>
     <item>Some attribute names have been changed for clarity.
      The attribute <code>src</code> of the element <file>copy</file>
      have been renamed to <file>dir</file>, <file>prop</file> have been
      renamed to <file>property</file>. The <file>target</file> attribute
      of the <file>filter</file> element have been renamed <file>file</file>.
     </item>
     <item>The <code>Task</code> interface have been simplified (the
      <code>done()</code> method, quite tricky to implement, have
      been replaced by <code>next()</code> much simpler). Task writing
      should be much easier.</item>
     <item>The source code is commented and API docs rely in
      the <file>api</file> subdirectory of the docs.</item>
     <item>UML diagrams rely in the <file>uml</file> subdirectory.</item>
    </list>

   </sect>

   <sect><title>Version 0.2 (2000-06-11)</title>

    <list>
     <item>The documentation have been translated in French.</item>
     <item>A bug in the launching script for Windows have been
      corrected (thanks to Romain Guy).</item>
     <item>A bug related to Windows platform detection have been
      corrected.</item>
     <item>The jar file for the Sun's XML parser have been included.</item>
    </list>

   </sect>

   <sect><title>Version 0.1 (2000-06-07)</title>

    <list>
     <item>The entire architecture have been improved.</item>
     <item>First fully functionnal version.</item>
     <item>First distributed version.</item>
    </list>

   </sect>

   <sect><title>Version 0.0 (2000-06-01)</title>

    <list>
     <item>Demo version to validate the concept.</item>
    </list>

   </sect>

  </sect>

  <p><imp>Enjoy !</imp></p>

 </text>

</article>

<!-- Local IspellDict: american -->
