<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//CAFEBABE//DTD article 1.0//EN"
                         "../dtd/article.dtd">

<article lang="en" 
         id="vsql.doc.en" 
         date="2001-10-15" 
         email="casa@sweetohm.net"
         author="Michel CASABIANCA">
 
 <title>VisualSQL 0.5</title>

 <abstract>
  <p>VisualSQL is a simple visual tool to display the result of SQL queries 
   in a table. It is Open Source (under the GPL license).</p>
 </abstract>

 <text>

  <sect><title>Installing VisualSQL</title>

   <p>To install VisualSQL, you must first :</p>

   <enum>
    <item>Install a Database (you can use 
     <link url="http://www.postgresql.org">PostgreSQL</link> which is
     an Open Source Relational Database).</item>
    <item>Install a 1.2 or 1.3 Java Virtual Machine. You can download one
     for free on <link url="http://java.sun.com/j2se">Sun's web 
      site</link>.</item>
    <item>Download a JDBC driver for your Database (you will find
     some for PostgreSQL on <link url="http://jdbc.postgresql.org">this
      site</link>).</item>
   </enum>
   
   <p>To install VisualSQL, type <code>java -jar vsql-.jar</code> in
    the directory of the archive. This will launch the auto installer.
    You must then drop the JDBC driver for your database in the <file>lib</file>
    directory of VisualSQL. Windows users must edit the <file>bin\vsql.bat</file>
    file to add the driver jar file in the CLASSPATH. If your driver's 
    archive is a zip file, simply rename it to make a .jar file.</p>

   <p>The latest version of VisualSQL is on 
    <link url="http://www.cafebabe.net/html/vsql.en.html">my web 
     page</link>.</p>

  </sect>

  <sect><title>Building VisualSQL</title>

   <p>To build VisualSQL, you will need Ant version 1.3, you will find it on 
     <link url="http://jakarta.apache.org/ant">Apache web site</link>.
    Go to the <code>prj</code> directory and type <code>ant all</code> to 
    rebuild from sources.</p>

   <p>To generate the doc, you will need SAT, my set of Ant tools. You can
    find it on my 
    <link url="http://www.cafebabe.net/html/sat.en.html">web page</link>.
    To generate the installer, you will need FiJI, my installer generator.
    You may find it on my <link url="http://www.cafebabe.net/html/fiji.en.html">
    web site</link>.</p>

  </sect>

  <sect><title>Using VisualSQL</title>

   <p>Type <code>vsql</code> on the command line to launch VisualSQL. The 
    application will look like :</p>

   <figure url="vsql.screen.png"/>

   <p>First, you must connect to the database:</p>

   <enum>
    <item>Type in the name of your JDBC driver class. This should be
     included in your driver's documentation. For PostgreSQL 7.0, the
     driver class is <file>org.postgresql.Driver</file>.</item>
    <item>Enter your database URL. This depends on your database and
     your driver's documentation should document this. For PostgreSQL, 
     this is something like <file>jdbc:postgresql://localhost:5432/myDB</file>.
    </item>
    <item>Type in user name and password (if any).</item>
   </enum>
   
   <p>Then click on the button to connect. If connection fails, a dialog
    box should detail the error. When connected (no error message), you 
    can send SQL queries to the database by typing them in the text area 
    and clicking on the query button. The result is shown on the lower pane.
    You can display previous queries with arrows (up for previous and
    down for next ones).</p>

   <p>You disconnect from the database when quitting or by clicking on
    the disconnect button. When quitting, your configuration is saved
    in a configuration file (<file>~/.vsql.properties</file> on Unix or
    <file>&lt;VSQL_HOME&gt;\vsql.properties</file> on Windows). The query
    history (last 100 queries) is saved in a file (<file>~/.vsql.history</file>
    on Unix or <file>&lt;VSQL_HOME&gt;\vsql.history</file> on Windows).</p>

   <p>Key bindings are the following:</p>

   <list>
    <item><imp>Ctrl+Space</imp>: Connect/disconnect from the database.</item>
    <item><imp>Ctrl+Enter</imp>: Execute Query.</item>
    <item><imp>Ctrl+Up</imp>: Previous Query in the History.</item>
    <item><imp>Ctrl+Down</imp>: Next Query in the History.</item>
   </list>

  </sect>

  <sect><title>Configuration file</title>

   <p>The database connection properties are saved when you quit the
    application in the following properties:</p>

   <list>
    <item><imp>jdbc.driver</imp>: the JDBC driver to use.</item>
    <item><imp>jdbc.url</imp>: the database URL.</item>
    <item><imp>jdbc.user</imp>: the user name.</item>
    <item><imp>jdbc.password</imp>: the password for the user.</item>
   </list>

   <p>There are other properties you can change by editing the properties
    file:</p>

   <list>
    <item><imp>debug</imp>: to run the program in debug mode. The stack
     traces are printed on the console. Copy those stack traces to
     send a bug report. May have the values <file>true</file> or 
     <file>false</file>.</item>
    <item><imp>swing.icons</imp>: this is the set of icons to use in
     the interface. May have the values <file>swing</file> or <file>jlobby</file>.
     The Java Lobby icons are Copyright(C) 1998  by  
     <link url="mailto:dean@gallant.com">Dean S. Jones</link> and may
     be downloaded at <link url="http://www.gallant.com/icons.htm">www.gallant.com/icons.htm</link>.
    </item>
    <item><imp>swing.primaryX</imp> and <imp>swing.secondaryY</imp>: change
     those values to customize you interface. Those values may be decimal,
     hexadecimal (starting with <file>0x</file>) or octal (starting with
     <file>O</file>) values.</item>
   </list>

  </sect>

  <sect><title>License</title>

   <p>This software is free and released under the 
    <link url="http://www.gnu.org/copyleft/gpl.html">GPL</link>.
    You can find a copy of this license in the file <file>LICENSE</file>
    in the installation directory.</p>

  </sect>

  <sect><title>History</title>

   <sect><title>Version 0.5 (2001-10-15)</title>

    <p>Bug correction (query related key bindings were active even when 
     not connected to the database).</p>

    <p>Disconnection from the database on VM shutdown (using finalizer
     execution request on 1.2 VMs and a shutdown hook on 1.3).</p>

   </sect>

   <sect><title>Version 0.4 (2001-10-10)</title>

    <p>The program has been completely rewritten using a (supposed) clean
     object design.</p>

   </sect>

   <sect><title>Version 0.3 (2001-08-22)</title>

    <p>Bug corrections (the program didn't started if no history file
     was found in the user's home) and enhancements (tool tips on the
     column headers). Thanks to <link url="mailto:vixxes@noos.fr">Laurent
      ROMEO</link> for his contribution.</p>

    <p>Documentation updates.</p>

   </sect>

   <sect><title>Version 0.2 (2000-08-31)</title>

    <p>Directory tree changed, Hot Keys and theme added.</p>

   </sect>

   <sect><title>Version 0.1 (2000-08-30)</title>

    <p>Minor bug fix (related to the Connect button) and an enhancement
     (related to the History list).</p>

   </sect>

   <sect><title>Version 0.0 (2000-06-07)</title>

    <p>First release.</p>

   </sect>

  </sect>

  <p><imp>Enjoy !</imp></p>

 </text>
</article><!-- Local IspellDict: english -->
